<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Angliae tutamen, or, The safety of England being an account of the banks, lotteries, mines, diving, draining, lifting, and other engines, and many pernicious projects now on foot tending to the destruction of trade and commerce, and the impoverishing this realm : with reflections thereon of great import to all sorts of people / by a person of honour.</title>
            <author>Person of honour.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25244</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08801648</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08801648</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41892</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41892)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1273:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Angliae tutamen, or, The safety of England being an account of the banks, lotteries, mines, diving, draining, lifting, and other engines, and many pernicious projects now on foot tending to the destruction of trade and commerce, and the impoverishing this realm : with reflections thereon of great import to all sorts of people / by a person of honour.</title>
                  <author>Person of honour.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by John Whitlock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commercial policy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41892:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41892:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANGLIAE TUTAMEN:</hi> OR, THE Safety of England.</p>
            <p>Being an ACCOUNT OF THE <hi>Banks, Lotteries, Mines, Diving, Draining, Lifting,</hi> and other <hi>Engines,</hi> and many pernicious <hi>Projects</hi> now on foot; tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Deſtruction of <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Commerce,</hi> and the Impoveriſhing this <hi>REALM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>With Reflections thereon. Of great Import to all Sorts of People.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Perſon of Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author: And are to be Sold by <hi>John Whitlock,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41892:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41892:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ANGLIAE TUTAMEN:</hi> OR, THE Safety of England.</head>
            <p>THAT Commerce is the Soul of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, and the Life of theſe Three Siſter-Iſlands, <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> in their Situation the happieſt in the World, renown'd for the Courage of their Men, and ſecur'd by the Strength of their Shipping, envied and fear'd by their Neighbours, is well known to every Body; and therefore in the Preſervation and Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Commerce conſiſts their greateſt Safety and Glory: Commerce is the Fountain of Wealth, the true Foundation of all real Greatneſs. Our Inland Trade alſo ought to be provided for, and encourag'd with all imaginable Care and Caution; ill Practices and Abuſes at home prevented or ſuppreſs'd, as well as our Navigation ſecur'd abroad.</p>
            <p>Our chief Aim is to advance Honeſty, now in its Declenſion, and to diſcourage Knavery, now in Vogue and Practice, which has impudently aſſum'd another Name, foul Dealers calling themſelves Shrew'd Men,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41892:3"/>Long Heads, and Mercurialiſts; as if Wiſdom or Wit conſiſted in Sharping and Over-reaching each other. It is pity Cozening and Cheating ſhould be in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent with Negotiators, ſeeing that clear and round Dealing is ſo much an Honour to Man's Nature: The firſt, in the end, proves fatal and deſtructive to all Commerce, both Foreign and Domeſtick: The latter being found, after ſtanch Experience, to be the beſt Intereſt, and trueſt Policy.</p>
            <p>A fair and clear Diſcovery of many crafty Cheats, and villainous Knaveries, will be of vaſt Advantage to the Publick, in preſerving each Individual from the Rock on which ſo many have ſplit, and been undone. This Treatiſe will ſerve for a Buoy or Mark to the Nation, to beware how they are wheedled and drawn into theſe pernicious Projects following, <hi>viz.</hi> Banks-National, Land, Money, Paper or Notes, Orphans, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now on foot, and more preparing; Companies for Mines of Gold, Silver, Copper, Tin, Lead, Iron, Antimony, <hi>Lapis Calaminaris,</hi> &amp;c. Coals, Salt-Rock, and other En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines innumerable; Diving of many ſorts, to fiſh up Wreck, Guns, Tackle, Treaſure, Merchandize, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, Japanning, Glaſs-Bottles, <hi>Venetian</hi>-Metal, Leather, Linen <hi>Engliſh, Scotch, New Jerſey;</hi> Paper White, Blue, <hi>Engliſh, Iriſh;</hi> Japann'd, Printed-Hangings, Pearl-fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Salt-Petre, Sword-Blades; Waters of the <hi>New Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Conduit, Thames, Hampſtead, Shadwell,</hi> &amp;c. Wrecks, South-Sea, Coaſts of <hi>Spain, Portugal, France, England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Holland;</hi> Lifting-Engines, Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Engines, of ſeveral kinds, for Mears, Marſhes, Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, Mines of all ſorts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Luteſtring-Company, Lotteries for Money or Merchandize; New Settlements in <hi>Carolina, Penſilvania,</hi> and <hi>Tobago,</hi> and other Parts;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41892:3"/>Convex-Lights, and others; Fiſheries Royal and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate; Corporations or Companies of many kinds; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, Leaſes, Grants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With ſome few more Projects now in Agitation.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not pretend to obſerve any ſtrict Method in the Proſecution of this Deſign, Order and Conduct be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt out of Faſhion, at leaſt among Men of Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, though it yet remains in Force and Eſteem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Soldiers and Scholars; Martialiſts and Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts always keep a <hi>Decorum,</hi> and, indeed, retain a true Senſe of Honour and Honeſty, and have it always in their view; whereas the Traders make no great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions to either, having long ſince abandon'd both.</p>
            <p>And although I did not mention the Bank of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> yet I ſhall dare to have one fling at that, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding 'tis ſo ſtrongly entrench'd and fortified, and ſo thinks it ſelf ſecure againſt all Attempts of open Force, or private Stratagem; Artifice won't do, but Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument may; and thoſe that touch Men in their moſt ſenſible Parts, their Pockets, uſually make the deepeſt and moſt durable Impreſſion upon them.</p>
            <p>This Bank was to the Amazement of our ſelves, as well as Aſtoniſhment of our Enemies, (the <hi>French</hi>) compleated in leſs time than could have been imagin'd; and, if the fix'd Summ had been double, it would have been all ſubſcrib'd. We ſhall applaud the Wiſdom of our Senate in the Eſtabliſhment of it, to anſwer the Emergencies of the State, (now involv'd in a doubtful and difficult War,) and we ſhall pleaſe our ſelves with a grateful Reflection on the Wealth of our Kingdom, which appear'd eminently great at that time; and the more, becauſe a Million-Lottery was alſo then on foot.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:41892:4"/>
            <p>Yet even this glorious Bank, as much as it dazles our Eyes, has its real Inconveniences, (and ſo, you may ſay, will all Humane Eſtabliſhments have,) and thoſe very great ones too, not feign'd or ſuppos'd, (for we ſpeak without the leaſt Prejudice or Partiality) but ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial and true ones, and ſuch as are viſible, and have been (and will be more and more every Day) found very detrimental to Trade; it has given a mighty damp to Commerce, which is (as I ſaid before) the Life and Soul, the very Being of this Nation, by cutting off, at one Blow, all Perſonal Securities, which was the main Help and Support of the Trading-Part of this Realm. It muſt be confeſſed this Bank has its Excellencies; for, beſides what have been already mention'd, it has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt cruſh'd ſeveral ſorts of Blood-ſuckers, mere Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, Uſurers and Gripers, Goldſmiths, Tally-Jobbers, <hi>Exchequer</hi>-Brokers, and Knaviſh Money-Scriveners, and Pawn-Brokers, with their Twenty and Thirty <hi>per Cent.</hi> at their Girdles, Procurations and Continuations, and the reſt of that Fardel. The good Conduct and fair Management of this Bank, by Men of the beſt Heads and faireſt Reputation, does in ſome Meaſure atone for ſome of the Defects.</p>
            <p>'Tis not to be thought this Bank, as much as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be for the Publick Good, will let their Money lie idly in their Cheſts, for which they pay Three <hi>per Cent.</hi> or be contented with ſo ſmall a Gain as one and a half or two <hi>per Cent.</hi> but rather will fall upon Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polies, engrocing of Merchandize, clandeſtinely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd, and ſecretly carried on in other Mens Names, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis againſt the Letter of their Eſtabliſhment, through which they'll wade, when Proſpect of great Profit preſents; and it being to be ſhared amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41892:4"/>'tis not to be expected they ſhould (like lawleſs Robbers) fall out, tell Tales, and impeach each other. By this means, I ſay, by the vaſt Summs they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready by them, they'll break in upon other Mens Trade and Buſineſs, their Livelyhood, nay, their very Property, being under Regulations in Bodies Politick, fenced by Law. Hence Bankrupts and Deſtruction of Families enſue, the mercileſs <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws making no Proviſion (as in other Countries) for thoſe unhappy Perſons, but Priſon or Payment of Debts, to them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. All Trade lying open, and in common, would be of more certain Utility than inclos'd and incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; which has been, and is, fatal to this poor King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, exhauſted by many Methods, of which I ſhall treat in their proper Place.</p>
            <p>Alas! the great Dividends the <hi>Bank</hi> has already made, and is preparing to make, and the hopeful and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous Condition (to uſe their own Words) their Affairs are in, ſpeak plainly, and tell all the World in honeſt <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> that one Part of the Nation preys upon t'other; the mighty Gains that have ariſen to them, ſince their Eſtabliſhment, being no leſs than Twenty <hi>per Cent.</hi> muſt be a Loſs ſomewhere, for 'tis all within our ſelves; and though <hi>Banks</hi> may very well be compar'd to ravenous Birds, yet in this they exceed them, the Vultures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not preying upon each other. We are all of one Nation, and if we could extract Profits from Foreigners 'twould do well, but from one another, enriches not the Publick one jot; for Native Wealth, though fairly ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led among the Individuals, and great in the whole, can never render a Kingdom or State ſo Conſiderable at home, and formidable abroad, as Domeſtick Riches aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and improv'd by Foreign Commerce; though
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41892:5"/>'tis not Importation but Exportation inriches a Nation; 'tis not what is conſumed among our ſelves, nor are Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagants of ſuch Advantage to a Commonwealth, as ſome weak People think and affirm: I ſay, 'tis not what we eat, drink, or wear, or uſe otherways, at home, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our own, or Foreign Produce, that is benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to us, but the ſending abroad vaſt Quantities of home-made Cloths, Stuffs, Serges, Worſteds, Camblets, Silks, Brocades, Linens of various ſorts, Stockins of Silk, Worſted, Yarn, and Cotton, Gloves of the ſame; Caps, Hats, Shooes, Boots, Saddles, Bridles; and, in a word, all ſort of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Manufactures, and bringing in the Produce of other Countries in part, or Bullion, or Coin, or good Debts remaining, 'tis this that turns to the beſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt; therefore the <hi>Weſt</hi> is much better for us than the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade; one wonderfully inriches, t'other mightily impoveriſhes us: The firſt by Employing thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Poor, and making Multitudes of Rich much Wealthier; the t'other by draining us of what we want moſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Gold and Silver, which they ſend thither to a vaſt value, which in time muſt make the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> the richeſt Spot in the World; very little or none of our Manufactures go thither: And what have we in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for our Bullion and Coin? but what we want not, but may very well be without: 'Tis only what grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Pride, Folly, and Luxury of the Age; which is always fondeſt of what is deareſt, and is fetch'd fartheſt; valuing things according to the Price and Vogue, not Uſe and Service.</p>
            <p>Beſides, thoſe Voiages murder our Sea-men, (our chiefeſt Strength) hardly one in five returning alive, or at leaſt not found; nor can all the Benefits which we are told ariſe by that Commerce, atone for the Damage
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41892:5"/>we viſibly ſuſtain by it; 'tis apparently the Intereſt of the <hi>Indian</hi> Princes to encourage and court us to Trade with them, becauſe we fetch their numberleſs Manufactures, painted Toies, and brittle Earth, and pay our vital Blood for 'em, our Lives, our Gold and Silver.</p>
            <p>But one word more to the <hi>Bank</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> before I make an end of that Head: Since their Eſtabliſhment, there has been a ſenſible Decay and Declenſion of our Inland Trade, known to the greateſt Part of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and may be atteſted by an Army of Witneſſes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, to their Sorrow, in the <hi>Temple, Alſatia,</hi> and the <hi>Mint:</hi> And thus much may be ſaid, without conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Oracle, if we get happily out of this War, they will not be long liv'd, I mean, hardly ever renew their Leaſes, never more be confirm'd by Parliament, but the State-Debt paid in, and they diſſolv'd: They hoard up all the good, and pay out the bad Money; they cauſe the Riſe and Fall of Moneys at their Pleaſure, which occaſions Difficulty and Incertainty in Trade: And this is ſo well known, that 'tis paſt all Conteſt, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.</p>
            <p>And now for the National <hi>Land-Bank,</hi> which ſtands ſo high in Fame, and makes ſo great a Noiſe in the World, is ſo Charming and Attractive, that Eſtates to a very great value have been ſubſcrib'd in the ſeveral Counties of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> in a very ſhort ſpace, in much leſs time than was expected; beſides, vaſt Summs of Money, a Committee and Truſtees being cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, a Deed agreed on and ſettled, a Company form'd, Directors appointed, Officers elected, and all Things diſpos'd to put this wonderful Project in Execution, to raiſe Lands to thirty Years Purchaſe, by reducing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to three <hi>per Cent.</hi> the Profits to be divided amongſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41892:6"/>the Subſcribers. Theſe Offers are plauſible and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, varniſh'd and gilded over, baited with mighty Hopes of prodigious Gains to all that ſhall be concern'd, to ſome, no doubt, there will be, <hi>viz.</hi> to the Projectors, Managers, and Officers; but, it is ſuch a Hotch-Potch and Medley, ſuch a Body, made up of ſuch ſtrange Members, ſubtil, politick and deſigning Men, that all pretend the Good of the Re-publick only, when that of the Re-private is chiefly intended: The firſt is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd to tickle and draw in the Eaſie and the Credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; but the laſt deſign'd from the very beginning; for never did Projector yet aim at any thing ſo much as his own particular Profit and Intereſt, though they always pretend the contrary. The fair Face and Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide this <hi>Bank</hi> carries, wins abundance to the Belief of its Deſign to be Good, but a little time will ſhew the naked Truth, the Juggle and Impoſture will appear, and the <hi>Bank</hi> fall, to the ruine of many, who will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd and confounded in the Intricacy and Difficulty thereof; the ſecret and under-hand Intrigues carried on, to cajole and wheedle ſome to Subſcribe, to encourage others; large Promiſes made of greater than common Profits to ſuch; ſome Men of Quality, others of Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, all of Eminency, prevail'd upon to Countenance the Project, to give Life and Reputation to it: Theſe Contrivances, I ſay, to mention no more, give ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cauſe of Jealouſie and Suſpicion, if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe at the bottom; but the Snake lies cloſe, and in its due time will ſtir, hiſs, bite and ſting the greateſt Part concern'd.</p>
            <p>The Injuries this, as well as other <hi>Banks,</hi> will inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably bring upon the Home-Trade of this Kingdom, and Foreign Commerce too, are ſo plain, and ſo obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41892:6"/>that 'twould be but time loſt to ſay any thing more upon that Head: All this and more poor <hi>England</hi> will find too true, and, I fear, too late. Each petty Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiator feels it already in his Buſineſs, and in his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, and is ſenſible 'twill encreaſe upon him more and more each Day he lives; and the more <hi>Banks</hi> are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd, the more Damage will Commerce receive in every Branch of it. What I have ſaid, and ſhall offer further in the following <hi>Pages,</hi> proceeds from no other Sentiments than what ariſe from the Love of my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, whoſe Proſperity I wiſh more Paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than my own, and for whoſe Sake and Intereſt I now draw my Pen, being wholly unconcern'd in <hi>Trade,</hi> or <hi>Banks,</hi> or <hi>Projects</hi> of any kind whatſoever; and ſo, conſequently, what I have already deliver'd, or ſhall, is void of all ſiniſter Deſign, private or particular Aim, Revenge, or Reſentment; and there are many Pretenders to Publick Good, but no ſuch ſincere Purſuers of it as my ſelf.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Money-Bank</hi> follows next, and made a great Noiſe at firſt, and fill'd apace with Subſcriptions; but now the laſt mention'd, and this (like two Whores, being both of a Trade) cannot agree, but are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually pelting one another with Reflections and Wipes, both in Writing and Print, in Letters and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements, and pretend to Predict the Condition and Fate of each other; which, I believe, they may very well do, without conſulting the Stars, or the Pretenders to the Knowledge of their Influence; indeed they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may beſt do it, knowing the falſe and ſlippery Foundations they are built upon, and the undue Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures they take to ſupport them, notwithſtanding the ſubſtantial and ſolid Security of <hi>terra Firma.</hi> This
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41892:7"/>
               <hi>Bank</hi> is indeed more Self-intereſted and Narrow-ſoul'd than the former, which is more diffuſive in their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits to every individual Subſcriber, who ſhall ſnack, whereas the Money here is to be ſhar'd by the Lenders and Managers only. This <hi>Bank</hi> differs ſome ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from t'other, but in its Tendency to the Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Trade in general, is of the ſame Malifick Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>The next that preſents is of <hi>Paper,</hi> of <hi>Notes,</hi> or <hi>Bills of Credit,</hi> to paſs to and fro, from one to another, in lieu of Coin; 'tis ſaid to be impracticable, though the zealous Projector thinks it not ſo; nay, ſome ſay, unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, though he denies that alſo; and threatens if it won't go down here in <hi>England,</hi> it ſhall travel to <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> or <hi>France;</hi> in the laſt of which Places, he is ſure it will be receiv'd and cheriſh'd, the Neceſſity of their Affairs will reduce it ſpeedily into Practice, and the great Soul of that Prince will ſoon find a Reward for the Projector, ſuitable to the Greatneſs and Utility of this wonderful Propoſal, which will enable him to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer all his Neighbours, his Paper holding out longer than their Money.</p>
            <p>But good Nature, common Prudence, and love of the Country where he lives, keeps the Projector from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſoming this Secret to Foreign Powers, of which this Kingdom is not (as he ſays) worthy, becauſe they will not liſten to their true Intereſt, ſo heartily and chearfully offer'd in this time of their Exigency, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd in an expenſive Foreign War; which, when it will end, no Man now alive knows, or can make any tolerable Conjecture.</p>
            <p>I have no Spleen againſt this Undertaking, in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, having been courted to be a Member, with of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41892:7"/>of advantagious Terms, which I ſcorn'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected; but, I think, this would have a fatal Tendency, and confound rather than benefit us: The chief Deſign of the Maſter of this ineſtimable Jewel being, as I am fully ſatisfied, to have the Top-Conduct of the Affair, and, beſides, a mighty Salary, to have a round Summ for his Service: There is Self-Intereſt and Advantage at the bottom of all theſe Deſigns. The <hi>Money-Banks</hi> will all fall in upon Monopolies; though, I think, this may not, for Paper will never paſs ſo currently as Coin, without a National, I mean a Parliamentary Security, which, I believe, will hardly ever be obtain'd.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Orphans Bank,</hi> I think, is the next in ſucceſſion, and in that we will keep the right Line. The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences were fair and plauſible for the Eſtabliſhment of this Fund. Compaſſion and Tenderneſs to the Poor and the Diſtreſſed; indeed thus far it has done Good, it has quicken'd that old Debt; which, though it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd new Birth from an Act of Parliament, yet it wanted Warmth, Heat and Vigour, which it has gain'd by this means, and the Credit of that Debt is much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd by this Method; which is a real Good, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands Applauſe: But yet even at the bottom of this Charitable, and Pious Project, Self-Intereſt and Private Profit lies ſecurely entrench'd, and that will be found at the foot of all their Accompts, let them ſay what they pleaſe to the contrary. We ſhall make the nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler Tranſition over this, becauſe it has not the ſhadow, but ſubſtance of real Good; and merits our Praiſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than our Cenſure, if they keep within due Bounds, without running upon Monopolies; to which they'll be mightily tempted, whenever they find themſelves Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of much Caſh; and they being many of 'em Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41892:8"/>will know how to lay it out to the beſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for themſelves. The Fate of this, as well as the preceeding <hi>Banks,</hi> we ſhall attend with Patience: They are but newly born, juſt come into the World, do not ſhew themſelves in their proper Colours, or act by their own free Will, but rather under the Tutorage and Protection of others. A little time will ſhew us the good or the Evil that waits upon them.</p>
            <p>But now for the <hi>Embryo-Banks,</hi> which are begot, but not brought forth; (for theſe Repoſitories are as fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile as the Womb, and by mingling Matters procreate, and ſend forth their like,) what ſhall we ſay to them, that are not yet ſhap'd, or lick'd into form? They are much of the ſame Nature with the reſt, and will dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer when they come into the World <hi>nomine tantum.</hi> I have been amongſt theſe latter Projectors, and find their Plots all tend the ſame way, they are like the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the preſent Age, they write but what was written before, only give the Book a pleaſant new Title, which goes a great way in the Sale of it; the greateſt part of the World being Soft and Silly, and taken with Sound and Emptineſs; the modern Men, I mean, the t'other Sett of Projectors all hug themſelves with the glorious Proſpect of great Profit, ariſing from their own dear Notions (as they call them, though they are borrow'd, being but Grafts or Cyans, young Sprouts from an old Tree;) the great Salaries, and the Lumps of ready Money, hugely pleaſe them; the living in Committees at the Publick Expence, is no inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Matter, becauſe it ſaves them ſo much in the Pocket. Theſe will be pernicious and deſtructive if ever they come abroad, and therefore ſhould be cruſh'd, while an Egg only. If, like thoſe Noble, Univerſal
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41892:8"/>(not National only) <hi>Banks</hi> of <hi>Venice, Amſterdam, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa, Paris, Hamburg,</hi> they tended to the Promotion of Trade, and Security of Coin; they would merit an Eſtabliſhment: Such a one as the <hi>Bank</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (the beſt of them all, our All) has obtain'd; but theſe are Muſhroons, very inſipid, without abundance of good Pickle; they come out of Seaſon, and will hardly be worth the Preſerving.</p>
            <p>The <hi>London-Bank,</hi> as one is to be call'd, which is now preparing for the Preſs, that it may appear in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick as well as the reſt; is of the ſame Leaven, propos'd to be manag'd by the Principal Magiſtrates and Chief Citizens, to give Reputation and Encouragement to the Project: But in this the Projectors will infallibly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, becauſe the Chamber-Conduct was ſo bad, and the City yet remains without Credit upon that very ſcore, the poor <hi>Orphans</hi> Sufferings are ſtill freſh in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; and we all very well know that it is very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, nay, almoſt impoſſible to retrieve either Publick or Private Reputation, when ſunk. Not to go ſo far back as the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, who raſhly in a ſtrait ſeiz'd ſome Thouſands of Pounds, coining in the <hi>Tower,</hi> belonging to private Hands; and though His Majeſty immediately publiſh'd a Proclamation, to aſſure them they ſhould have their Principal with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in a very ſhort time, which they really had, yet that unhappy Prince could never recover his Credit, to be able to borrow any conſiderable Summ of his Subjects: The like Fate befel his Son and Succeſſor, <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, in the <hi>Exchequer</hi> Buſineſs, nothing but Parliamentary-Faith could bring him in any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney after that ill Accident; although, to do that King Right, he did his utmoſt to ſatisfie the Bankers and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41892:9"/>their Creditors, and had put it into a good Method, if his Brother <hi>James,</hi> when he came to the Crown, had not fallen in upon it, and ſtop'd its Currency; which gave a mighty damp to it; which, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the many ſtruglings it has had ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution, (as 'tis generally call'd,) it has not been able to overeome.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Topick of <hi>Banks,</hi> with a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſwaſive to all People, of all Ranks and Profeſſions, and of both Sexes, to beware how they are drawn into theſe Snares; they are pernicious Practices, and ought to be kick'd out of the Commonwealth. And, if what has been ſaid be not ſufficient to prevail upon them, that have not yet been caught, to have a Care of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as alſo on thoſe that are ingag'd, in time to draw off, before they have gone too far, and thereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Misfortunes that will inevitably attend them; I ſay, if the Arguments I have laid down, and enforced, together with the foul Practices I have diſcover'd, and expos'd, be not of Weight enough to deterr them from parting ſo tamely and fooliſhly with their Land, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and Credit, let them proceed, and fall into the Net, ſpread for them, by crafty and deſigning Men.</p>
            <p>The poor <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation runs a madding after new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, Whims, and Projects: And this unhappy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient my dear Country-men have in their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, they are Violent, and proſecute their Projects ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly for a time, but, not meeting with Succeſs, they give over, and abandon all Hopes of ever doing any Good, never reflecting upon their ill Management, or undue Methods.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:41892:9"/>
            <p>What a Run of <hi>Lotteries</hi> have we had! That, like a Plague, have ſpread themſelves over the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, of the ſame Date, though, I believe, not Dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the <hi>Bank;</hi> every Body is ſick of them; the Town was pleas'd at firſt with the Novelty of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, but now glutted and nauſeated. With what haſte they all flew to put in their Money we well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; the mighty Hopes they ſed themſelves with, each gaping for the higheſt Benefit; and what golden Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes they made themſelves, and how painfully they attended the coming up of their bad Fortune we can't forget; it was for a time the only News, and ſole En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of the Town: They, poor Innocents, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſider'd the Projector's Aim, no leſs than the Parſon's Profit, One in Ten; or, the Royal Deduction in Prize-Goods, of Ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> would ſatisfie them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and how foully they were manag'd, every Body is now ſatisfied. But the <hi>Merchandize-Lotteries</hi> were worſe than the Money, though both pernicious to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Why do we thus labour and toil, plot and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive to Cheat one another? If we could Cheat the <hi>Dutch,</hi> or the <hi>French,</hi> 'twould be ſomething; but, to ſharp one another, is a very dull Story; and, I doubt, our Neighbours are too cunning for us; I think they have been ſo hitherto: 'Tis pity the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould be ſo eaſie and ſo weak. The old decay'd Merchandize and Rubbiſh that was whip'd off by means of theſe Roguiſh Lotteries, was incredible in its Quantity; all ſorts of Goods, almoſt all ſorts of Trades concern'd; the People were tickled with the Propoſals of prodigious Profit, when the propoſers intended it only for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, making above Thirty <hi>per Cent.</hi> advance: And this out of the poor Rogues Pockets that were thus
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41892:10"/>wheedled. The general Complaints that have been ſince made, of the many Abuſes and Impoſitions in thoſe <hi>Lotteries,</hi> are clear Indications of their Baſeneſs. And indeed the People have been ſo damnably cheated of their Money, every manner of way, that, I think, they have no need of Diſſuaſives to venture again, their own Sufferings are ſufficient to convince them it is their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to forbear.</p>
            <p>The Companies for <hi>Mines</hi> of <hi>Gold, Silver, Copper, Tin, Lead, Iron, Antimony, Lapis-Calaminaris, Coals, Salt-Common,</hi> &amp;c. have made a great Noiſe in the Town, and, indeed, throughout the whole Kingdom; to draw in People to join with them, they have made uſe of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Tricks and Stratagems; firſt they pretend a mighty Vein of Gold, Silver, or Copper, to be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd in a Piece of Ground of their knowledge, then they agree with the Lord, or Patentees, for a ſmall Year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rent, or a Part reſerv'd (about a Fifteenth) to him, or them, to grant them a Leaſe for Twenty one Years to dig that Land; which they immediately fall to, and give out 'tis a very rich Mine; then they ſettle a Company under Articles, divide it into Shares, uſually 400, chuſe a Committe, a Clerk, and Transfer-Book, and pretend to carry on this Work to the Benefit of the all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors; who, at the beginning, purchaſe Shares at a low Rate, <hi>viz.</hi> Ten Shillings, Twenty, or a Guinea, then all on a ſudden they whip up the Shares to Three, Five, Ten, nay, Fifteen Pounds a Share; then they fall to Stock-Jobbing, which infallibly ruines theſe, and all other Projects; thoſe principally concern'd, ſell their Intereſt, draw off, and wholly quit the Affair, which, by this and other means of underhand dealing, trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41892:10"/>and ſharping one another, falls to the Ground, and is abandon'd by every Body. Nothing thrives, where ever they admit Stock-Jobbing, it has ſpoil'd more good and really uſeful Deſigns and Inventions, than all the ill Accidents that have attended them beſides. To fetch Wealth out of the Bowels of the Earth, without doubt mightily enriches a Nation, and to employ ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Hands gives Bread to abundance of poor labouring People, which is a good thing; and many Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers have got great Eſtates by Copper, Tin, Iron, and Lead Ore's and Coals, and their Affairs uſually ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, and turn to a very good Accompt, when man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ag'd by a few honeſt diligent Men; for of great Uſe and Conſumption are theſe Things in the State, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what are ſent abroad: But theſe latter Years have produced a Knot of Projectors that aim only at getting a little Money into their own Pockets, to ſupport their Neceſſities, which are preſſing and pinching, without any regard to the Good of the Company in which they are engag'd, which cauſes a Rupture, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the whole Deſign. 'Tis ſaid, that <hi>Neceſſity is the Mother of Invention, and that Poverty whets Mens Wits:</hi> Thus much I believe, That ſharp and narrow Fortunes put Men upon Plots and Contrivances how to over-reach, circumvent, draw in, and cheat one another, to ſupport themſelves, and wade through a difficult and painful Life; but 'tis pity Honeſty is ſo much abandon'd, which carries with it, in all Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiations, whatſoever ſo much Honour and real Eſteem in the World; that it is eſtabliſh'd by a Proverb, and yet almoſt left out of Practice.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:41892:11"/>
            <p>The next Project we ſhall conſider, is the <hi>Diving-Engines</hi> of divers kinds, all crept abroad ſince the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up of the Duke of <hi>Albemarl</hi>'s Wreck, (as it was commonly call'd for diſtinction, and becauſe he was concern'd in it:) This Wealth that was fetch'd out of the Sea (after ſeveral chargeable and fruitleſs At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts,) was trumpeted all over the World, and ſet Mens Heads at work to get more; in order thereto, Patents were obtain'd from the Royal Fountains, for the ſole Fiſhing of Wrecks on the Coaſts of <hi>America, Spain, Portugal, Ireland, Scotland, England,</hi> &amp;c. and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties form'd of Merchants and Gentlemen to manage this Affair in ſeveral Kingdoms; and then came up Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-Engines of various make, ſome like a Bell, others a Tub, ſome like a compleat Suit of Armour of Copper, and Leather between the Joynts, and Pipes to convey Wind, and a <hi>Polyphemus</hi> Eye in the Forehead to give Light, and pretended mighty Feats, ſtaying under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many Hours, and giving out by Publick Shews, and Trials on the <hi>Thames,</hi> the vaſt Utility of theſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, although the foreſaid Wreck was clear'd, and vaſt Quantities of Pieces of Eight taken up by naked Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, both White and Black, without the leaſt help or want of any ſuch Engine; yet People were taken with Noiſe, led by Phancy, and ſo hook'd: Patents were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo gain'd for the ſole Uſe of theſe Gimcracks, for Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Years to come; and then about making the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines they went, and after ſeveral Alterations and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendments, which took up two or three Years, (and at laſt good for little,) they divided the whole Project into Four, and afterwards as many Hundred Shares, and preſented ſome to People of Note and Figure, to give Reputation to the Affair; and theſe doughty Names
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41892:11"/>were ſubſcrib'd to play the Part of a Shooing-Horn, and wheedle in the Eaſie; Treats and Money given to the Neceſſitous and Sharp, to bring their Friends and Acquaintance to ſee the Engines, who were tickled in the Ear with the vaſt Wealth of Gold and Silver that ſhould be taken out of the Sea with theſe Tools; and, being led by an avaricious Deſire of growing. Rich on a ſudden, they come in and were engag'd, paid down their Money, and had the pleaſure to ſee a Committee choſen, and Contributions of Ten Shillings or more <hi>per</hi> Share advanc'd, and Expeditions ſent forward to <hi>Scotland, Ireland, Scilly,</hi> and the Land's End of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and up and down upon our Coaſts; and the mighty Atchievements they perform'd, was taking up a few Iron-Guns, Chiney-Backs, and Ship's-Tackle, which anſwer'd not the End, nor Expences, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing eat up the Stock, and ſtop'd the further Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of the Affair: So theſe fine <hi>Diving-Engines</hi> lie by the Walls, are at reſt, and, for ought I know, may never more diſturb the World with their Noiſe and Nonſenſe. 'Tis ſtrange when we reflect what abundance of People have been drawn in and abus'd, of all Qualities, Gentle and Simple, Wiſe and Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; and really among 'em ſome Men of imcompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Parts and great Qualifications were caught, being allur'd with the Hopes of gaining vaſt Riches by this means: And here Stock-Jobbing alſo made its way, the certain Poiſon or Bane of all Projects though in themſelves never ſo good and uſeful; the Patentees got Money, and every Body elſe loſt, and ſo there was an end of that Matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dipping, Japanning, Printed Hangings, Pearl-Fiſhing,</hi> making <hi>Sword-Blades, Glaſs-Bottles, Venetian Metal, Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:41892:12"/>&amp;c. come next: The firſt Projectors and Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors have really got Money, had their Ends, but no Body elſe that I can hear of; and, while they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu'd in ſingle Hands, or a few, they throve and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, but when ever they fell to Stock-Jobbing, they certainly dwindled away, and came to nothing. Some of theſe are Uſeful, and may be for the Publick Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, but moſt of 'em are mere Whims, and of little or no Service to the VVorld, though they all proclaim loudly their VVorth and Goodneſs, and employ A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents to magnifie their Inventions, and wheedle in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and ignorant People; who, being charm'd with the Novelty of the Things, (though perhaps but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd, or borrow'd from ſome Foreign Nation) pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Shares, and ſo are cheated of their Money; which is worſe than High-way Robbing, for they come up Face to Face and demand our Money, and often fight for it before they get it, and ſometimes die in the Attempt; I ſay, theſe are open and declar'd Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and ſo proclaim'd by the State, but the t'other (by much the baſer) come with ſly Inſinuations, and, under the Vizor and Mask of Friendſhip, decoy in the honeſt well-meaning Man, and by painting over the Propoſals in lively Colours, tinctur'd with Gold (though lighter than the Leaf) or Silver, impudently aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Impoſſibility of failing of making great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, obtain their curſed Deſigns, and ſo go on, playing the <hi>Knave;</hi> which Title of Honour no Quack in the VVorld bears with more Patience than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: now, if theſe Things were manag'd fairly and candidly, and above board, they would meet with far greater Encouragement: But 'tis ſaid theſe VVars have begat Poverty, and that has produc'd theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41892:12"/>the Crown has been open-hearted, and readily granted Patents for the Encouragement of Ingenuity; and more have been taken out within theſe Seven Years laſt paſt than in Fifty, nay a Hundred before; I mean for trifling Engines and Whims. Oh, a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent gives a Reputation to it, and cullies in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: They had almoſt as good purchaſe Land in <hi>Terra incognita,</hi> for they meet here with very ſlippery Bargains; and, notwithſtanding, the plain and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Breaches of Amity and Civil Society by theſe means, yet theſe pernicious Practices, to ſharp and cheat one another of their Money and Goods are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd; and all this ſo notorious and ſo very common, yet, I ſay, ſo eaſie and unwary are abundance of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that they are daily trapp'd: Projects, like Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, beget their like, and multiply wonderfully, Projects upon Projects, Lottery upon Lottery, Engine upon Engine: If any one Man gets conſiderably by a happy and uſeful Invention, abundance run im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately into it, and, in ſpight of the Patent, take with little alteration a Copy, and then out come the Propoſals in Print, the <hi>Gazettes</hi> and Publick Papers are cramm'd with Advertiſements, the fourth Column is entirely theirs: And thus they go on to ſpoil one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to abuſe others; and ſo the Publick ſuffers by their Folly and Knavery.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh, Scotch, Iriſh,</hi> and other Linen Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, if honeſtly and fairly manag'd, would be of infinite Advantage to all thoſe Places; and beſides the charitable dealing of Subſiſtence to the numerous Poor, would wonderfully enrich all the Proprietors, and be alſo for the Publick Intereſt; for the fewer Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41892:13"/>Commodities we conſume among our ſelves, the more we ſave, and conſequently get; and if we could be ſo happy to bring 'em to Perfection fit for Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to ſupply Markets abroad, we ſhould then pinch the <hi>Dutch,</hi> the World's common Carriers, and univerſal Traders, for the more they, or any Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers get from us, the poorer we are, and ſhall be. All due Encouragement has been given to theſe great Undertakings, the preſent King and late Queen per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them to be honour'd with their Names, which gave a mighty Reputation to them, their Fame roſe, and their Credit encreas'd, and abundance of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Condition were mingled, ſome led by Lucre, others by Love of their Country, (though of them the feweſt) puſh'd on the Buſineſs very vigorouſly, united and incorporated themſelves, choſe a Governor and Officers, Inſpectors and Comptrollers, actually ſet at work Spinners, and other Workers, Weavers, Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thought it would have produc'd great Profit, for the Actions mounted apace, and in great probability of being higher, when all on a ſuddain ſome greedy, mercenary, mean Spirits fell to Stock-Jobbing, and ſcar'd the Eaſie and Timerous, and brought the Actions down, abundance ſold off their Shares, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with their firſt Profits, which were conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, rather than to attend the hazard of making grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a little time, or loſing ſome of the preſent, and ſo by degrees, the Reputation of this mighty Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture ſunk here, and, I underſtand, is in a bad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and will hardly be able to hold up its Head, much leſs to advance any further: The ſame Fate, is fear'd, may attend the reſt. Now this was really a good Deſign, and it is pity it had not the good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41892:13"/>to flouriſh, they had brought Linen-Cloth to great Perfection, and had ſome <hi>Dutch</hi> Hands, and ſome few Heads to aſſiſt them; I wiſh they had had of the laſt: This was indeed a noble Undertaking, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited well of the Publick. By the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>Dutch</hi> we have hugely improv'd our Lands in the North-Parts of this Kingdom, by ſowing vaſt quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Lin-Seed, Rape-Seed, and others; and thence making Oils in great quantities, which we export in abundance, and conſume at home, in lieu of Foreign and dearer Oils, to our double Advantage; for the leſs of the Foreign are imported, and the more of our own exported, the greater is our Gain. The Profits that ariſe hence are much more conſiderable to the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords and Tenants, than thoſe of any Corn or Grain whatſoever; and how much more we might advance our Lands by ſowing Flax and Hemp-Seeds, if our Linen-Manufactures ſucceeded as they might, is plain to every common Underſtanding: But, I think, we are not deſtin'd to do our ſelves and our Country Good. I am ſorry that <hi>England</hi> is ſo barren of true Patriots, a word ſo Great and Glorious, that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Romans</hi> thought it a very great Honour, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu'd themſelves very much upon being ſo call'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>White, Blue,</hi> and <hi>Brown-Papers,</hi> made here in <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſhall be examin'd next. This good Fortune we in <hi>England</hi> have had to improve wonderfully in this Art, and though we cannot reach the <hi>French</hi> Perfection, yet we come pretty near it, and make much finer Paper than ever, which in this our Exigency, I mean the Prohibition of Commerce with <hi>France,</hi> is of very great Service to us; but our Hands
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41892:14"/>are dearer that are employ'd, we cannot work ſo cheap as the <hi>French,</hi> becauſe we muſt have Beef, Pudding, and ſtrong Drink, our People can't live upon Onions, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nips, and ſmall Soupes; beſides, our Linen-Manufacture miſcarrying, gives a damp to this honeſt and uſeful Undertaking; and it is a thouſand pities we can't raiſe Paper to the <hi>French</hi> Goodneſs, and lowneſs of Price, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'twould tend ſo vaſtly to our Advantage, in keeping us from laying out ſuch vaſt Summs of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney with <hi>France,</hi> for this Commodity alone, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Importing it from thence, we might Export it to other Countries; which would employ Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and enrich Hundreds. The Linen-Manufacture, on which it partly depends, and by which in great meaſure it ſubſiſts, being ſo much ſunk in its Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that 'tis fear'd 'tis at its laſt gaſp, irretrievable, ſtops the growth of this, which notwithſtanding is flouriſhing, and kekps its Head above Water; vaſt quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Paper are daily made here, and the Ragg-ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers hard put to it to ſupply us, though they bear a good Price, and has encreas'd that Profeſſion; that ſome are ſtarving, and others begging, who have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd me the ſcarcity of Raggs is great, and that the young diligent Collectors out-do the old, and go out in the Nights to the Dung-hills and Layſtalls to tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them over for this Merchandize, which at this time are mightily call'd for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Waters</hi> of <hi>New-River, Thames, York-Buildings, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don-Bridge, Shadwell, Conduit, Hampſtead,</hi> &amp;c. are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections all worthy of great Encouragement, and ſo the firſt has had, to the gaining of vaſt Eſtates by the Proprietors; though the unhappy Gentleman that began
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41892:14"/>the Work fell by it, and ſuffer'd extreamly in his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, which ought to have been made up by the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that receiv'd ſuch Benefits by his Brains; a grateful People would have erected a Monument to his fame; but we in <hi>England</hi> keep cloſe to an old Adage, <hi>Every man for himſelf, and God for us all.</hi> I think ſome Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours were ſhown the Deſcendents of this Great, though infortunate Undertaker, the <hi>Middleton</hi>'s, who bear his Blood, and carry his Name, were preſented with ſome Shares. This and the <hi>Thames</hi> Water have gain'd the Aſcendent, and much Money has been got by the latter: They are kept in good Hands, and the Stock-Jobbers, thoſe Moles, thoſe Underminers, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers, not ſuffer'd to come amongſt them, the Jack-Daws have been too hard for the Rooks, (as thoſe Gentlemen are call'd;) but now here are new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances of this uſeful Element, and humble Servant, Water, laid in the Earth; the Conduit for the City of <hi>London,</hi> which is better Water and cheaper, impoſing no Fine, which the <hi>New River</hi> arbitrarily and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably did, for which it is meritoriouſly puniſh'd, and the Proprietors clipt in their Profits, by the great fall of their Actions or Shares. The <hi>Hampſtead</hi> alſo will ſupply that End of the Town, <hi>Holborn,</hi> &amp;c. neareſt to which it lies; and the Terms are fairer and eaſier, which lop off more from the <hi>New River;</hi> but this laſt, I mean, <hi>Hampſtead-Water</hi> unhappily paſſes through ſuch Hands, that, in all probability, it will come to nothing, or turn to very ſmall Accompt; the Stock-Jobbers have broke in, and, I am of Opinion, will break out, outright; that is, ruine the Affair. Theſe are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally noble and commendable Undertakings, not Whims, or Maggots, Chimera's, or Airy Notions, but real, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41892:15"/>and ſubſtantial Deſigns of ſerving the Publick, and merit the Approbation of all Men; but the Eaſie and Credulous muſt beware of being drawn in to purchaſe Shares at too dear a Rate, and ſo be coſen'd of their Money, for the Credit of all theſe Water-Works is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly fallen, partly through ill Conduct, and ſome later Diſcoveries, and newer Works.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rock-Salt</hi> in this Rank leads the Van, deſerves our Praiſe, and ſhall have it; for that is ſo wonderfully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd by the Integrity of the Proprietors, and their Prudent Management, that it is ready to come to a Dividend; they are eſtabliſh'd in a Company, of Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and Traders, have built a Wharf at <hi>Frodſome</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> have form'd Correſpondencies in <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> whither they ſend great Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of this Commodity, which turns to a very great Advantage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salt-Petre</hi> ſhall be the next, but that has had a worſe Fate; great Summs of Money ſubſcrib'd and paid in, large Refining-Houſes built in four or five ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Places about this Town, Servants entertain'd, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors and Clerks appointed, Societies eſtabliſh'd, and a mighty Noiſe they made for a time, a loud ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Name, and of Quality, appear'd at the Head of them, and encourag'd the Affair, abundance of Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and Traders concern'd, all things diſpos'd in good Methods, a Foundation laid of future Profits, and thoſe extraordinary ones, and as durable as the preſent War, which call'd for their Commodity, and brought it to bear a great Price: But of all theſe Companies, not one, that I can hear of, has made any great Hand
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41892:15"/>of this Matter; it muſt be confeſt the firſt Projectors have had Succeſs, for they got by it, and then ſlunk away; the ill Conduct, and Admiſſion of Stock-Jobbers, together with ſome unlucky Accidents falling in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 'em, mightily diſcourag'd the Buſineſs, and ſtop'd the Progreſs of it, their Fires are out, their Houſes lie neglected, and begin to molder away, their Union diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, and a neceſſaay Project (at this time) loſt; and Gun-Powder, within this Month or five Weeks, partly by the falling off of this, and the loſs of five <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Ships, advanc'd from three Pound ten Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to four Pound ten Shillings a Hundred, and how much higher it may go I know not, for now the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Refiners, Gun-Powder Makers, and Ship-Chand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers have receiv'd Encouragement by the Miſcarriage of theſe Men, they'll do their utmoſt to take their Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Draining Engines,</hi> of divers ſorts, have been lately made, to clear Coal, Lead, Tin, and other Mines from Waters, which either ſoak in or ſpring up, to their hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance in their Working, damage and charge of the Proprietors; as alſo other Engines for Draining of Flats, Levels, Mears, Inundations, Springs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects might be of great Uſe and Benefit to the Publick and Private too, for the more Land we recover, and improve, the richer we grow; and that Soil which is under Water, is loſt to the Commonwealth, that Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Element doing here no manner of Good; the Earth is rich, being much of it Marl, the beſt of Land, and we are ſo unhappy in <hi>England</hi> to have many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Acres thus cover'd with Water, and which have been ſo, ſome, time out of mind, others but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41892:16"/>lately, all recoverable, and drainable, if proper Methods were taken, and with the help of theſe Engines (of which I have ſeen ſeveral) if fairly undertaken, and at much eaſier Rates than by the bodily Labour of hir'd Men; which to feed with Bread, and pay Wages, would prodigiouſly ſwell the Accompt, enflame the Reckoning, and render the Charge exceſſive, inſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and diſcouraging. That theſe Projectors have really done Service in the Mines, and effected what they pretended to is manifeſt, having actually earn'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween three and four hundred Pounds <hi>per Menſem;</hi> this I ſay is notorious to Thouſands in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and <hi>Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> who have been Witneſſes to the Operation; and 'tis but juſt this ſhould be encourag'd, for we intend not by this Diſcourſe to expoſe or diſcountenance In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, but quite the contrary, to ſupport and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance it; but, alas, good Inventions, and Schemes, have too often tack'd to them fraudulent Deſigns, of impoſing upon unwary People, and engaging them in what is very often injurious to their Purſes; and, in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> commonly prove palpable Cheats, which I am now labouring to prevent for the future, at leaſt as much as I can, by diſcovering the private Intrigues, ſecret Plots, and underhand Dealings of the Principal Projectors of this Kingdom, more fully and amply than any Body elſe can do; beſides, nothing of this Kind was ever attempted before, and therefore ſurely this will be the more grateful, ſeeing that it preaches up their true Intereſt in this World, which moſt Folks purſue more heartily and zealouſly than that of the t'other; which being at ſome diſtance, and matter of Faith, rather than Fact, they give themſelves but little trouble about.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:41892:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Luteſtrings, Alamodes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hats,</hi> of ſeveral ſorts, in imitation of thoſe made in <hi>France,</hi> for no other can I call it, for they do not come up to their Excellency, though wrought by Native <hi>French</hi> Men; where the Defect lies, is the Difficulty to diſcover, ſome ſay the Water, others the Gum, ſome one thing, ſome ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but this is certain, they are not of that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, Beauty, or Durability with thoſe imported from thence; though theſe Endeavours are mightily to be commended and encouraged, as they are by a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wear of them, (the Silks eſpecially) through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Kingdom; <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> have the <hi>French</hi> in ſome Plenty, becauſe the Prohibition of Commerce is not obſerv'd with the ſame ſtrictneſs as here. Theſe Companies have throve, and will, ſo long as they keep the Stock-Jobbers from breaking in upon them, all is loſt, inevitably gone, if they come there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Convex Lights,</hi> and others, are uſeful Inventions, and ought to be more regarded than they are, for the Houſe-keepers contribute but awkwardly towards their Encouragement; for by that means the Proprietors ſet them at too great a diſtance, ſo that they receive not each others Beams, but leave too great a <hi>Vacuum;</hi> they might be improv'd alſo in their Light, which ought to be clearer, and more diffuſive, whereas theſe have Darks. Several have loſt that have had Shares, and few (that I hear of) have gain'd any thing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; there are other Pretenders beſides the firſt; which has baulk'd the Buſineſs, for 'tis our unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in <hi>England</hi> (as I obſerv'd before) to invade each
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41892:17"/>others Invention, and by Trick and Artifice ruine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hopeful Undertakings.</p>
            <p>New Settlements in <hi>Carolina, Penſilvania, Tobago,</hi> and other Places, make a great Noiſe in the World. The firſt Planters far'd but ill, having waſted their Subſtance, without being able to reap the Benefit, laying only a Foundation for the next comer, who may ſucceed better; and, in all probability, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious People, who make up the Groſs of thoſe Colonies, (the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as they are commonly call'd) will cultivate, and improve a mighty Tract of Land in thoſe Parts, to their future Advantage; though, I think, to the Injury of their Native Country, which ſuffers now, and will more, by their abſence; and, I believe, it will be found impolitick to permit ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny People to abandon this happy Iſland, to Seat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a Soil ſo remote; for, I think, it is granted by all, That 'tis Number of Subjects, and not Extent of Territory, makes up the Greatneſs of a Prince; and, if ſo, we viſibly decline, for we are very thin of People at this time, having been exhauſted by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural and imprudent Perſecutions in the late Reigns, and by the long knocking War in this preſent. But, Thanks be to God, and our good Stars, our preſent Conſtitution, like Cloaths of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> make, ſits eaſie on our Bodies, and Minds too; and therefore 'tis pity but a ſtop were put to theſe <hi>American</hi> Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers, who having gone a great way towards their Eſtabliſhment in thoſe Places, are willing to go through with it, for their own particular Intereſt, without any Regard to that of <hi>Old England,</hi> who then ought to take Care of it ſelf, and keep thoſe Subjects at
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41892:17"/>home, who now have not Reaſon to retire, ſeeing they have Liberty of Perſon and Perſuaſion, and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty too! So well ſecur'd both for the preſent and the future.</p>
            <p>Fiſheries Royal, <hi>Greenland, Newfound Land,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are worthy our Care and Application: The firſt has been long talk'd of, and ſome Steps made to bring it about, but ſtill one ill Accident or another fell in, and damp'd it; 'tis now again on foot, I wiſh it good ſucceſs: That 'twill be of infinite Advantage to this Kingdom every Body knows, the Benefits are plain and obvious, and ſo well receiv'd, and ſo often told, they need not be mention'd; our Sage Senate will be ready to eſtabliſh this, as they did the <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which is like to flouriſh, notwithſtanding ſome Loſſes have already attended it. Indeed, I think it highly unreaſonable that the <hi>Dutch</hi> (whom I love as our Neighbours and Allies) ſhould come on our Coaſts, and take our Fiſh, and cure them, and carry them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and Trade ſo prodigiouſly, with them as they do, to the vaſt Advantage of their State, and to the inriching of ſo many particular People, and to the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying ſo many thouſand Hands, and filling more Bellies, breeding up great Numbers of Sea-men, which calls for our firſt Thoughts, and deſerves our moſt hearty Endeavours, they being our beſt Guard; and therefore ſhould have the greateſt Encouragement; for our Walls of Oak would not defend us, without their Hearts, all out as firm, ſtout and impenetrable. I ſhall ſay the leſs on this Head, becauſe ſo much has already been ſaid by others, and therefore ſhall conclude this Paragraph with a word or two more. We have now
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41892:18"/>got a KING after our own Hearts, a Prince whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt is ours, and who eſteems ours His, and who ſeems deſtin'd by Heaven to recover and eſtabliſh the ancient Honour and Eſteem of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Name and Nation, and who will joyn with us, and aſſiſt us in all Things that may tend to the encreaſe of our Wealth and Reputation; He will make us Formidable abroad, and Happy at home; his Victorious Arms will do the firſt, and his Wiſe Councils the laſt; He will preſerve and improve our Commerce, the beſt Support of his Government, and the ſweeteſt Flower in our Paradice; and though the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who chiefly vie with, and would rob us of this ineſtimable Jewel; I ſay, though they are his Country-men, yet we are his Subjects, he will cheriſh us and chaſtiſe them.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude, for 'tis high time, having ſpun out this Pamphlet longer than I intended, though I found Matter ſo flowing, that I could hardly give over; juſt as I am winding up, and cloſing mine, I underſtand there are new Books laid open for Annuities and Lot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, with which laſt I thought the Town had been tyr'd; it ſeems one is fled to <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> for there (if full) 'tis to be drawn. As for the Annuities, I find the Projectors by their Propoſals intend good Bargains for themſelves; which, indeed is the chief Aim they all have: Theſe as well as the former Projects, which I have diſtinctly conſider'd, will have fatal and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſequences; for, in the bottom of moſt, there lies a deep Deceit.</p>
            <p>Pray let us Reflect on the vaſt Number of Projectors in and about this City, how bare-bon'd they are, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41892:18"/>is, how few of 'em are Rich? Therefore we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, theſe Aery Gentlemen in ſome Meaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble Witches, who do harm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> others, but ſeldom good to themſelves: It is pity there is not a Regiſter of them, (as alſo of Lands, Houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) the poor Purchaſers of Shares from the firſt, and of Eſtates of the laſt, often meet with bad Bargains; and by that means, <hi>viz.</hi> of a Regiſter, they might eſcape the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſave their Money from being pick'd out of their Pockets, by theſe Camelions, who know no end of Projects, for what they get by one, they lay out in another; ſo that Poverty ſeems to be the conſtant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of Projectors as well as Poets.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>There is lately publiſh'd, <hi>SOlon Secundus:</hi> Or, ſome Defects in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws; with their Proper Remedies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sold by</hi> John Whitlock, <hi>near</hi> Stationers-Hall.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
